Welcome to part III of our MOOC "Web Engineering".
My name is Klaus Quibeldey-Cirkel. I am the instructor of this course.
The language of the videos is German, because this MOOC is part of a German university lecture at Technische Hochschule Mittelhessen (THM) and our students have a right to German lesson.
Anyway: In our times of globalization it doesn't hurt to have listened to one or another foreign language once in a while.
Now, let's get to our introductory video.
I will briefly explain the learning objectives of this course,
and the prerequisites for finishing the course successfully.
I will introduce you to our two projects:
A term project everyone needs to do.
And an optional, voluntary Scrum project in September in which you may participate offshore, i.e. from home online.
Finally, I'll give you the course dates for the homework and the final exam.
First, the course objectives:
There are two main proficiency objectives we want to convey:
1. Mastering the maintenance challenges of Web apps that need to be changed and brought into production often.
This means, the first objective is about engineering skills like build automation, performance and browser testing, and continuous deployment.
That is, iterating the process of getting your code ready for production once your have edited your changes.
2. What is special about this MOOC, is that you will have a chance to practice collaboration in a continuous delivery environment during two weeks in September:
Practicing soft kills/team skills by collaborating with your peers, communicating, and coordinating.
We will offer this project during a two-week offshore scrum project in September.
You will work together on a project with the students of THM.
It will be very interesting to organize both "offshore" and "onshore" students together in a project and to elaborate on it on a daily basis
and to come up with a release at the end of the project.
What will this Scrum project be about?
We want to further develop a prototype app called THMCards, i.e. add new features known from apps like "Quizduell" and others.
This project is an super modern open source, single page and full stack javascript app.
With a NoSQL database and Node.js as backend.
Let's get to the prerequisites:
The must-have hardware prerequisites are:
1. access to a fast internet connection
2. a modern multi-core computer (desktop/notebook) with at least 4 GB RAM
The software prerequisites are:
1. any OS will do, we will use a virtual environment
2. you need to a have a Unix/Linux terminal/command shell installed on your computer
If you use a Windows OS, you need to make sure that your command shell offers the full functionality of a bash shell.
3. Oracle Virtual Box should be installed as virtualization software; however, we can talk about alternatives.
What are the brain ware prerequisites?
Web Engineering III builds on the competences gained in Web Engineering I and II.
It is not necessary that you have attended those two courses, but it is required that you have the knowledge you could have acquired in those courses.
1. You should have a solid command of Unix/Linux commands, of HTML5, and JavaScript, because we will build, test and deploy apps based on these techniques.
You should be willing to participate in a two-week Scrum project.
However, attending the Scrum project is not required to get the Certificate of Accomplishment or the Statement of Participation.
This slides gives an overview about the six chapters of this MOOC.
The tools I marked with a curly bracket are the tools that we will learn to use based on the ARSnova app which most of you got to know through some surveys during part 1 and 2 of the MOOC.
All these tools are available as open source tools online, the build pipeline, the project environment, GitLab and the project management tool Redmine.
By practicing these tools on the productive, running ARSnova app, you will be able to study them in depth.
There are four Homework Assignments planned for this course:
All of these assignments serve to prove that you have understood the contents of the videos and additional materials provided in this course
and that you are able to apply that knowledge using the respective tools.
You will learn to create test plans with Apache JMeter
by putting the ARSnova app under load and then watching the response times and if the app works as expected.
You will use Selenium for GUI tests,
that means, you will script the interaction with the browser and play back the scripts in different browser products
to check if the app is cross-browser compatible.
We will use Jenkins as our build environment.
The objective here is being able to formulate and execute Ant Maven build scripts.
SonarCube is an open source analytics tools, that creates a static analysis of ARSnova and produces different metrics that we will learn how to interpret.
Now, let's have a look at the term project:
For the term project, it is absolutely necessary that you provide an open source HTML5 app which you have developed yourself or
that you can develop such an app within the next few weeks. This app should be have a certain degree of usefulness.
This app will be published on the web and be publicly available.
The sources (your Git repository) will also be made public for learning purposes.
At the end of the term project, you will have to submit your term project in the form of the following list of deliveries:
- You have to publish your source code in a public Git repository. Your sources must include a so called Vagrant file.
The vagrant file allows creating virtual development, test and production environments via a terminal command locally on your computer.
- Apply the homework assignments you practiced on the ARSnova app to your app:
i.e. test plans with Apache JMeter,
test scripts created with Selenium
the Maven Ant/Jenkins build scripts,
and the QA metrics generated with SonarCube.
We will provide you with a publicly available source code management infrastructure for your term project
which you may also use for other projects if you like.
The SCM infrastructure will include the following tools (among others):
These are just the main tools that cover the learning objectives:
GitLab, a version management hosting system
comparable to GitHub but offering the possibility to add private repositories.
The build environment set up with Jenkins (formerly Hudson)
The project management tool Redmine including the Scrum plugin Backlogs.
CloudControl - introduced in Web Engineering I and II - as cloud hosting service for your web apps.
What to expect from the final exam?
There will be 10 questions about the contents of all six chapters of Web Engineering III that need to be answered within 60 minutes.
During the final exam you will be asked to submit your term project.
The final exam will take place during the last week of July.
The grading process depends on the type of certificate you want to achieve:
For a Statement of Participation, your peers will review your project.
For a paid Certificate of Accomplishment, the project will be graded by a course instructor.
Your project will then be commented and your grade will be stated on the certificate.
There will also be a diploma supplement stating the course contents.
Your identity will be verified and it will be certified, that the certificate was acquired under supervision and.
The authenticity of the certificate will also be guaranteed.
What types of certificates can be obtained in this MOOC?
The prerequisites for all types of certificates are the same:
- your activity progress indicators must show 80% fulfillment on all units which can be achieved by watching the course videos and answering the quizzes
- submission of all homework assignments
- passing of the final exam
- your term project must fulfill the requirements
After successfully finishing all of the above requirements, you can download a Statement of Participation free of charge
To get a paid Certificate of Accomplishment, your ID needs to be verified. The proctored exam will take place online. The fee is 99 Euro.
Due to popular demand, we will introduce a new, special kind of performance record in this third part of Web Engineering.
A few years ago, the Mozilla foundation launched Open Badges (see http://openbadges.org).
Open Badges are digital indicators of real world skills and achievements (see Wikipedia).
The visual representations contain further information (metadata ) that is displayed when someone clicks on such a badge.
Such metadata include the issuer of the badge and the criteria/requirements that were necessary to obtain the badge.
It may also contain much more information like the course contents etc. The person eligible for such a badge may publish it on his/her website, blog, wiki or wherever on the internet he/she seems fit.
To obtain Open Badges from THM, you need to fulfill two prerequisites:
1. You need to finish this third part of Web Engineering successfully by acquiring a Statement of Participation.
2.You need to participation successfully in the two-week Scrum Project in September.
These badges will be issued free of charge.
Finally, some important course dates:
The homework assignments will be published on a weekly basis at the end of each weekly chapter.
Altogether, there will be 4 homework. You will have two weeks to finish and submit each assignment.
However, there will be some overlap, because we want to finish the course within a timeframe of 6-7 weeks.
The final exam will take place during the last week of July. It's up to you to decide when you want to take the exam within this timeframe.
The exam lasts 60 minutes and may not be interrupted during this time.
The optional offshore Scrum project will take place during two weeks in September.
We will determine those two weeks by the help of an ARSnova survey.
Good luck with the videos, the quizzes, the homework and your project.