In this screencast, I want to explain the structure of an Apache JMeter test plan.
I will use the ARSnova use case "Instant Feedback" as an example.
Let's start with the system under test, ARSnova,
and look at the scenario "Instant Feedback"
We start ARSnova in our vagrant-production machine.
First, you log in as guest.
Next, you enter a session that you have created before, in this case PerfTest.
By tapping on "Give Feedback" and choosing a Feedback option, you can give the teacher feedback if you can follow the lecture.
When we do our performance test later, the bars in this diagram will reflect the actions of the virtual users.
Later, when you perform the use case under load, you can tap the icons on this page directly (without having to tap on "Give Feedback on the preceding page).
Now, let's get to the test plan.
I have prepared two scenarios:
The first scenario (Small Lecture Hall) with 10 virtual users who start the scenario within 5 seconds (ramp up period) and run the use case once (loop count 1)
The second scenario (Large Lecture Hall), is the same as before, but with 100 simultaneous virtual users.
As User Defined Variable there is the Session ID.
When you work with your own session, you will have to change the value for session key.
Next, the users have to log in, this will be done via the Guest Login.
For this purpose, we use a Random Variable with randomly generated values.
These values will be generated for each user separately (Options > Per Thread(User): True).
In real life, the users will then consider which option they want to tap. This period is called Think Time oder Wait Time.
We assume that this Think Time will be 1 to 5 seconds, and will configure this Think Time as a Random Variable for each user individually.
Then, the users need to give feedback in the way described before. There are 4 values.
From "I can follow you" to "You have lost me".
Internally, these values are defined as integer values 0 to 3.
Again, the values are generated randomly for each user individually.
For the samplers (HTTP request controllers) we define - for convenience's sake - the URL and the port.
In our case, the Web Server is localhost (or 127.0.0.1) and the Port Number 8080.
We want to simulate a realistic browser, therefore we tell JMeter to load all resources in each run (Retrieve All Embedded Resources).
That is, images, JavaScript (although JMeter does not interpret JS), videos, audio, external sources etc.
We allow four parallel HTTP requests on a TCP connection (Use concurrent pool. Size: 4).
ARSnova uses cookies for the security architecture in the backend.
In the HTTP Header Manager, we tell JMeter that we use application/json as exchange format for all requests and responses.
Therefore, we can define this format as a general header value.
No, we will get to the activities the virtual user has to perform in the use case scenario "Give Feedback" of this test plan.
First, the user has to log in. In the HTTP Request form you can see the detailed data that is exchanged.
It is a GET request. The necessary GET-parameters are type, user, and role. The user Guest ID was defined as a random variable.
Once the user is logged in, he/she needs to log in to a session.
To do this, the session ID has to be added to the URI in the path field: i.e. session/$(SESSIONKEY).
Then the number of active users is queried (indicated by the badges on the house icon on the start page of a session) using the path /session/$(SESSIONKEY)/activeusercount.
Next, the actual scenario starts. It is embedded in a Loop Controller which repeats the scenario 10 times.
That is, the virtual user gives his/her feedback ten times.
Between each of these actions, there is a random Think Time of 1 to 5 seconds. In the Constant Timer the Thread Delay is set to the Think Time variable ($(TIMER))
Give Feedback is a POST request with the respective body data, in this case only a number as a code for the selected option $(FEEDBACK).
Next, the feedback result is queried.
The number of feedbacks is indicated by the badge on the feedback icon.
Once the loop is over, the user is logged out (Guest Logout).
We have defined some listeners.
As you may well know by now, we can add many more.
I have chosen some of the plugins from the Google Code Project.
I will explain them briefly.
These are standard listeners. The scenarios are listed. But let me best explain this with an example.
Let's delete all sampler data of the preceding run and then run the test plan again.
You can see that the virtual users log in linearly.
The bar chart shows that the first users have already given their feedback.
Let's walk through the individual views.
The Aggregate Report provides a table with the scenario and the individual actions in that scenario.
The Result Tree show the activities as a list. You can have a look at the protocol of each individual request and response.
The results are also available as a table.
The next Listener is the Load Profile
The graph shows, that the 100 users logged in within 5 seconds.
Next a very popular metric, Hits per Second.
At the beginning, when the 100 users were logged in, we have some vigorous swings.
Out of these two, you can build a composite graph.
For example, you can overlay the Load Profile with the Hits per Second (at the moment, there is no data, we will wait until the next run).
The next listener shows the Response Times Over Time for the individual activities.
The scenario has almost finished. Now we could test the user experience under load by tapping on the icons and observing the reaction of the system.
As you can see, now it takes a while until you can see a reaction when we tap an icon. At the second and third tap the reaction is again faster.
Looking closely, we see that the scenario is already finished and there was no load anymore.
We should have performed the test while the 100 users were active (KQC moves the mouse cursor around an area in the diagram).
The red line represents the users. The blue line represents the session (login). After 16 seconds the last user has logged in.
Then the actual use case is performed: 100 users giving feedback (green line), 10 times in a row, superimposed ...
After having given their feedback, the users begin to log off (brown line).
Now we can work with the Composite listener.
There is a list of all available sources.
Now you can start overlapping graphs to draw conclusions.
This is the load profile.
Now we add the Server Hits per Second.
The composed graph shows heavy traffic at the beginning during the login, while it is quite regular during the actual use case scenario of giving feedback.
During logout, the swings are again more vigorous.
You can now add others listeners you had activated before.
It is also interesting to have a look at the successful and failed transactions.
In this case, there were no failed transactions.
My high-performance iMac with 4 cores and 16 GB RAM did not produce any failures.
I recommend having a look at the performance of your system as well, the impact of the scenario on your CPU, memory utilization etc.
The task of the homework assignment is to run two scenarios in parallel.
To do this, you have to configure the test plan accordingly.
Also, you are supposed to limit the individual scenarios in time.
All these settings are available in the options. You will learn about all these options while you work through the documentation, videos and other material.