Welcome to the last chapter of Web Engineering 3: "QA Deployment Pipeline"
At the end of this chapter you will have learned how to build such a pipeline locally
and which stages and jobs in these stages are important for quality assurance.
I will give you a brief outline in this unit, the details will be explained in the following units.
Each commit into the source code version control system triggers a build process and the corresponding unit tests will be executed.
When the build process was successful, several quality assurance steps will be run.
At the end of this process, the quality assured software will be deployed.
All these steps can be freely defined for your project.
Finally, a smoke test is run to make sure that the software runs as expected.
We will have a closer look at some of these quality assurance stages and the respective tools.
e.g. GUI tests, i.e. acceptance tests (remember the automation pyramid).
Many projects are not tested on lower levels by rely on the final functional test.
Non-functional quality tests can be performed in parallel (even if the diagram shows them sequentially).
e.g. performance tests with Apache JMeter, security tests, WAI tests (accessibility tests), usability tests etc.
Either in parallel or subsequently, a static analysis of the source code is performed, and an API documentation is automatically generated.
For this analysis we will use the tool SonarQube and have a brief look at it.
However, we cannot explain all the metrics of quality code within the framework of this course.
At the end of this chapter you will have built such a pipeline for your project.
As a UML sequence diagram (UML = Unified Modeling Language), the QA deployment pipeline is as follows:
As you will know if you study software engineering seriously the sequence diagram is structured as follows:
At the top, there are objects that trigger actions when activated - these actions are represented as little boxes .
Atypically, we have two time axes:
The lifeline of an object on the y-axis and the time of the transactions on the x-axis.
Here, the stages are represented as software classes: version control, build and unit tests, automated acceptance tests etc.
The developer commits code changes into the version control system.
This process triggers the first stage in which the software is build
and all unit tests are run.
If a unit test fails (represented by a red box), the developer receives feedback about the failure.
Feedback can be given via different channels, one possibility is via email - KQC opens email tool.
This is an example feedback mail from the Open Source platform Travis CI which we will also use in this chapter.
In the example on the left, the build was successful; on the right the developer is informed of a failure, the build was not successful.
If the build process is successful the next stage in the pipeline is triggered, in this case the acceptance tests.
If the acceptance tests fails, the developer/developer team gets feedback again.
If this stage is successful, the next stage is triggered. Here, the trigger is manual, i.e. a person has to approve it.
In this example, a person will test the user interface and check if it behaves as expected.
If the QA build pipeline is passed successfully, a new release is ready for deployment.
The QA pipeline as described here represents the learning objectives of this course.
What are the learning objectives?
You will learn how to design and implement such a  QA deployment pipeline.
Designing means, identifying the stages and jobs that are relevant for your project and create the architecture of this deployment pipeline.
Using the examples of ARSnova and THMCards, you will experience that a commit will indeed trigger this pipeline and
that - ideally - a single commit can result in a new release.
All this we will study and implement using the de facto industry standard Jenkins.
To make sure that the public build in the cloud is always functional and avoid "Who broke the build?" problems, a local Private Build is implemented. When the pipeline is passed locally, you can be sure that this will also be the case in the public build.
We will inspect the results of the static code analysis with SonarQube to see what is important (keyword: technical debt).
Homework Assignment #3:
Your task is to implement a private QA Deployment Pipeline for your own web app project.
Or, if you do not have your own project - it must be open source and publicly accessible in Github - you may use THMCards.
As prove of your implementation, you have to submit a screenshot of your QA deployment pipeline and the URL of the web app project released via your QA pipeline.
The deadline for submission of this homework and for the semester project is August 3, 2014, 23:59 CEST.
The semester project basically consists of this homework plus parts of previous homework assignments plus a build pipeline created in the cloud with the Open Source platform Travis CI and a browser testing platform called Sauce Labs Open Sauce.
Here is a screenshot that shows an example pipeline:
This screenshot is taken from the documentation of the plugin.
The build process can be started manually.
Here, the 8th build.
The information in the green "Test" box shows the person who triggered the test, the date and the runtime. By clicking on the button, you can open the log.
You can also trigger the build directly within the individual stages in this case.
Here, you see two stages in parallel: the green one has passed, red would be a fail, and the yellow one is still running, i.e. it is unstable, there is also a progress indicator.
You could click on it to see it in detail.
The blue stages are waiting for execution, deployment into a pre-stage environment and manual approval for production.
The history of all builds is shown on the vertical line.